Center for the Humanities at Tufts Records UA243
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Center for the Humanities at Tufts Records
circa 2006 -- 2018
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Center for the Humanities at Tufts
UA243
20.33 Gigabytes
52 Digital Object(s)
.5 Linear Feet
This collection contains the records of the Center for the Humanities at Tufts.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list.
Accruals
Further accruals are expected.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred by the Center for the Humanities at Tufts, 2016-2018.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in three series: Mellon Sawyer Seminar in Comparative Global Humanities; 2018 accessions; and Newsletters.
Biographical / Historical
The Center for Humanities at Tufts was established circa 2008, according to citations in the 2008-2009 Factbook, to foster interdisciplinary humanities work in comparative literature, comparative religion, world history, philosophy, anthropology, and the arts, to innovate new research and reflection. The Center hosts public lectures, seminars, conferences and colloquia by visiting artists, writers, and scholars, and brings together faculty, postdoctoral, and dissertation fellows. Fellows participate in a research seminar and attend monthly public events with distinguished visiting scholars.
Related Materials
Department of English Records, 1906-2016. Tufts University. Digital Collections and Archives. Medford, MA.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains videos of public lectures delivered as part of the Mellon Sawyer Seminar in Comparative Global Humanities series, transcripts of said lectures, and PDF exports of Storify collections of tweets sent during the lecture. It also contains videos of two events sponsored by CHAT, flyers and brochures for CHAT events from 2008 through 2016, CHAT office files, and newsletters published by CHAT for academic years 2016-2017 and 2017-2018.
- Mellon Sawyer Seminar in Comparative Global Humanities, 2016 -- 2017; UA243.001; 16.129 Gigabytes 11 videos, 11 TEI transcriptions, and 9 PDFs; 20 Digital Object(s)
  Conditions Governing Access
  This series is open for research
  Scope and Contents
  Includes video of lectures given as part the Mellon Sawyer Seminar in Comparative Global Humanities.
  - South Sudan: The Road to Civil War, 2016-09-21; UA243.001.00001
    Video of a lecture by Mahmood Mamdani on international relations, African politics, and questions of crime and punishment in the case of mass violence in civil war situations such as South Sudan.
    Mamdani, Mahmood, 1946-
  - Migrations, Islands, and the Creative Economy, 2016-10-13; UA243.001.00002
    Open for research.
    Video of lecture by Françoise Lionnet in which shares perspectives on recent artistic and literary works inspired by migrant crises in both the Indian Ocean and the Mediterranean sea and focus more specifically on the Comoros archipelago and the island of Mayotte, that "ultra peripheral" region of "Europe," she considers the multilingual work of poet and dramatist Soeuf Elbadawi to test the critical effectiveness of literature in the world as agent of cultural change. This lecture was presented as part of the Mellon Sawyer Seminar in Comparative Global Humanities.
  - Colonialism, Slavery, and the Archive: Old and New Practices, 2016-11-04; UA243.001.00003
    Video of a panel on old and new practices of archiving and curating among scholars and writers, activists and artists, engaged in the histories and legacies of colonialism and slavery. This panel was presented as part of the Mellon Sawyer Seminar in Comparative Global Humanities.
  - Plantation Dispossession and the Futures of Black Embodiment, 2016-12-06; UA243.001.00004
    Video of a panel exploring the futures of Black embodiment, both futures-past and futures-present, and the place of the Black body in the history of the present, and the futures to which it signals. This panel was presented as part of the Mellon Sawyer Seminar in Comparative Global Humanities.
  - Mahmood Mamdani, "South Sudan: The Road to Civil War" Twitter Storify export, 2016-09-28; UA243.001.00005
    PDF export of a Storify created from tweets sent during Mahmood Mamdani's lecture "South Sudan: The Road to Civil War" delievered as part of the Melon Sawyer Seminar in Global Humanities.
  - Françoise Lionnet, "Migrations, Islands, and the Creative Economy" Twitter Storify export, 2017-03-01; UA243.001.00006
    PDF export of a Storify created from tweets sent during Françoise Linonnet's lecture "Migrations, Islands, and the Creative Economy" delievered as part of the Melon Sawyer Seminar in Global Humanities.
  - CHAT Lost Histories Twitter Storify export, 2017-03-01; UA243.001.00007
    PDF export of a Storify created from tweets sent during a panel entitled "Colonialism, Slavery, and the Archive: Old and New Practices," part of the Melon Sawyer Seminar in Global Humanities.
  - CHAT: Plantation Dispossession and the Futures of Black Emobdiment Twitter Storify export, 2016-12-05; UA243.001.00008
    PDF export of a Storify created from tweets sent during a panel entitled "Plantation Dispossession and the Futures of Black Embodiment," part of the Melon Sawyer Seminar in Global Humanities.
  - Comparative Postcolonial Theory and the Question of Chinese Empire, 2017-01-26; UA243.001.00009
    Lecture by Shu-mei Shih exploring how the emergence of Shinophone studies is altering the landscape of postcolonial theory. This lecture was presented as part of the Mellon Sawyer Seminar in Comparative Global Humanities.
  - Colonial Memory and Trauma, 2017-02-16; UA243.001.00010
    Lecture by Debarati Sanyal and Stef Craps exploring how coloniality may compel us to rething the very structures of "memory" and "trauma" within the humanities. This lecture was presented as part of the Mellon Sawyer Seminar in Comparative Global Humanities.
  - CHAT: Colonial Memory and Trauma Twitter Storify export, 2017-02-16; UA243.001.00011
    PDF export of a Storify created from tweets sent during Debarati Sanyal and Stef Craps's lecture "Colonial Memory and Trauma" delievered as part of the Melon Sawyer Seminar in Global Humanities.
  - The Social Life of DNA, 2017-02-23; UA243.001.00012
    Lecture by Alondra Nelson consering how ancetry genetics (data derived from human bodies) is today employed to make raical statesments and justice claims aobut the past in the present. This lecture was presented as part of the Mellon Sawyer Seminar in Comparative Global Humanities.
  - CHAT: Alondra Nelson, "The Social Life of DNA" Twitter Storify export, 2017-02-23; UA243.001.00013
    PDF export of a Storify created from tweets sent during Alondra Nelson's lecture "The Social Life of DNA" delievered as part of the Melon Sawyer Seminar in Global Humanities.
  - Rethinking the Human: Epistemology/Therapeutics, 2017-03-09; UA243.001.00014
    Lecture by Emily Martin and Lawrence Cohen. This conversation centers the project of rethinking the human in the project of rethinking intellectual boundary-making, constellating innovations in medicine, technology, and clinical therapeutics as horizons for humanist ethics and counter-ethics. This panel was presented as part of the Mellon Sawyer Seminar in Comparative Global Humanities.
  - Empire of Religion, 2017-03-28; UA243.001.00015
    Lecture by David Chidester considering the genealogy of comparative religion. This lecture was presented as part of the Mellon Sawyer Seminar in Comparative Global Humanities.
  - The Politics of Human Rights, 2017-04-03; UA243.001.00016
    Lecture by Judith Butler considers the operations of human rights in critical legal studies, political thought, and postcolonial theory, with consideration of situated struggles in various global locations. This lecture was presented as part of the Mellon Sawyer Seminar in Comparative Global Humanities.
  - Sovereignty, Settler Colonialism, Territoriality and Resistance, 2017-04-20; UA243.001.00017
    Lecture by Audra Simpson and Jessica Cattelino which considers practices that seek to create alternative sovereignties, geographies, and conceptions of belonging and intimacy. Funded by the Andrew Mellon Foundation, Tufts Collaborates, and the Center for Humanities at Tufts. This lecture was presented as part of the Mellon Sawyer Seminar in Comparative Global Humanities.
  - Religion's Imperial Pasts, Global Futures Twitter Storify export, 2017/03/28; UA243.001.00018
    PDF export of a Storify created from tweets sent during a lecture by David Chidester entitled "Empire of Religion," part of the Melon Sawyer Seminar in Global Humanities.
  - The Politics of Human Rights Twitter Storify export, 2017/04/03; UA243.001.00019
    PDF export of a Storify created from tweets sent during Judith Butler's lecture "The Politics of Human Rights," part of the Melon Sawyer Seminar in Global Humanities.
  - Sovereignty, Settler Colonialism, Territoriality and Resistance Twitter Storify export, 2017/04/20; UA243.001.00020
    PDF export of a Storify created from tweets sent during a panel with Audra Simpson and Jessica Cattelino entitled "Sovereignty, Settler Colonialism, Territoriality and Resistance," part of the Melon Sawyer Seminar in Global Humanities.
- 2018 accessions, circa 2006 -- 2018; UA243.002; 4.2 Gigabytes; 4 Folder(s); 2 Digital Object(s)
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged in received order.
  This series contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list.
  This series contains videos of two events at CHAT: the first titled "Material Worlds: Genealogies of Race and Nature" by Mel Y. Chen, Associate Professor of Gender and Women's Studies at the University of California, Berkeley; Jake Kosek, Associate Professor of Geography at the University of California, Berkeley; and Alexander Blanchette, Assistant Professor of Anthropology, Tufts University. In this symposium, Chen, Osek, and Blanchette explore alternative biologies of race and racism, not through the most common routes of blood, skin or gene, but through other material biologies and rethinkings of life, matter, human, nature, and machine. The second event titled "Readings from The Blue Clerk, ars poetica" features poet, novelist, and essayist Dionne Brand reading from her book, The Blue Clerk (McClelland and Stewart and Duke UP, 2018). This series also contains flyers and brochures for CHAT events from 2008 through 2016, and CHAT office files.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Transferred by CHAT, 2018, accession UA-2018-049, UA-2018-064, and UA-2019-029.
  - Material Worlds: Genealogies of Race and Nature, 2017-11-14; UA243.002.00001; 1 Digital Object(s); 3804 Megabytes
    "Material Worlds: Genealogies of Race and Nature" by Mel Y. Chen, Associate Professor of Gender and Women's Studies at the University of California, Berkeley; Jake Kosek, Associate Professor of Geography at the University of California, Berkeley; and Alexander Blanchette, Assistant Professor of Anthropology, Tufts University.
  - Readings from The Blue Clerk, ars poetica., 2018-01-31; UA243.002.00002; 1 Digital Object(s); 709.43 Megabytes
    "Readings from The Blue Clerk, ars poetica." Dionne Brand reads from her latest book, The Blue Clerk (McClelland and Stewart and Duke UP, 2018).
  - Event flyers and brochures, 2008 -- 2010; UA243.002.001.00001; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Transferred by the Center for the Humanities at Tufts, 2018, accession UA-2018-064.
  - Event flyers and brochures, 2011 -- 2016; UA243.002.001.00002; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Transferred by the Center for the Humanities at Tufts, 2018, accession UA-2018-064 and UA-2019-029.
  - Event flyers and brochures, undated; UA243.002.001.00003; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Office files, circa 2006 -- 2013; UA243.002.001.00004; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    20 years from the date of creation.
    Transferred by the Center for the Humanities at Tufts, 2018, accession UA-2019-029.
    This file contains board meeting minutes and agendas, reports, proposals, correspondence, drafts, and other office files.
- Newsletters, 2016 -- 2018; UA243.003; 30 Digital Object(s) 30 digital objects comprising 30 files; 5 Megabytes
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  This series is open for research.
  This series contains PDF versions of email newsletters published by the Center for the Humanities at Tufts from academic years 2016-2017 and 2017-2018.
  - Center for the Humanities at Tufts Newsletter, 2016-09-19; UA243.003.00001; 1 Digital Object(s); .08 Megabytes
  - Center for the Humanities at Tufts Newsletter, 2016-10-03; UA243.003.00002; 1 Digital Object(s); .14 Megabytes
  - Center for the Humanities at Tufts Newsletter, 2016-10-17; UA243.003.00003; 1 Digital Object(s); .12 Megabytes
  - Center for the Humanities at Tufts Newsletter, 2016-10-31; UA243.003.00004; 1 Digital Object(s); .26 Megabytes
  - Center for the Humanities at Tufts Newsletter, 2016-11-14; UA243.003.00005; 1 Digital Object(s); .16 Megabytes
  - Center for the Humanities at Tufts Newsletter, 2016-11-28; UA243.003.00006; 1 Digital Object(s); .08 Megabytes
  - Center for the Humanities at Tufts Newsletter, 2017-01-23; UA243.003.00007; 1 Digital Object(s); .14 Megabytes
  - Center for the Humanities at Tufts Newsletter, 2017-02-06; UA243.003.00008; 1 Digital Object(s); .12 Megabytes
  - Center for the Humanities at Tufts Newsletter, 2017-02-13; UA243.003.00009; 1 Digital Object(s); .13 Megabytes
  - Center for the Humanities at Tufts Newsletter, 2017-02-20; UA243.003.00010; 1 Digital Object(s); .11 Megabytes
  - Center for the Humanities at Tufts Newsletter, 2017-03-06; UA243.003.00011; 1 Digital Object(s); .07 Megabytes
  - Center for the Humanities at Tufts Newsletter, 2017-03-27; UA243.003.00012; 1 Digital Object(s); .14 Megabytes
  - Center for the Humanities at Tufts Newsletter, 2017-04-14; UA243.003.00013; 1 Digital Object(s); .07 Megabytes
  - Center for the Humanities at Tufts Newsletter, 2017-09-07; UA243.003.00014; 1 Digital Object(s); .14 Megabytes
  - Center for the Humanities at Tufts Newsletter, 2017-11-13; UA243.003.00015; 1 Digital Object(s); .1 Megabytes
  - Center for the Humanities at Tufts Newsletter, 2017-11-20; UA243.003.00016; 1 Digital Object(s); .09 Megabytes
  - Center for the Humanities at Tufts Newsletter, 2017-12-13; UA243.003.00017; 1 Digital Object(s); .23 Megabytes
  - Center for the Humanities at Tufts Newsletter, 2018-01-09; UA243.003.00018; 1 Digital Object(s); .24 Megabytes
  - Center for the Humanities at Tufts Newsletter, 2018-01-23; UA243.003.00019; 1 Digital Object(s); .3 Megabytes
  - Dionne Brand reading announcement, 2018-01-31; UA243.003.00020; 1 Digital Object(s); .18 Megabytes
  - Center for the Humanities at Tufts Newsletter, 2018-02-05; UA243.003.00021; 1 Digital Object(s); .2 Megabytes
  - Center for the Humanities at Tufts Newsletter, 2018-02-12; UA243.003.00022; 1 Digital Object(s); .2 Megabytes
  - Center for the Humanities at Tufts Newsletter, 2018-02-20; UA243.003.00023; 1 Digital Object(s); .29 Megabytes
  - Center for the Humanities at Tufts Newsletter, 2018-03-05; UA243.003.00024; 1 Digital Object(s); .21 Megabytes
  - Center for the Humanities at Tufts Newsletter, 2018-03-12; UA243.003.00025; 1 Digital Object(s); .31 Megabytes
  - Center for the Humanities at Tufts Newsletter, 2018-03-15; UA243.003.00026; 1 Digital Object(s); .08 Megabytes
  - Center for the Humanities at Tufts Newsletter, 2018-03-26; UA243.003.00027; 1 Digital Object(s); .1 Megabytes
  - Center for the Humanities at Tufts Newsletter, 2018-04-02; UA243.003.00028; 1 Digital Object(s); .44 Megabytes
  - Center for the Humanities at Tufts Newsletter, 2018-04-17; UA243.003.00029; 1 Digital Object(s); .16 Megabytes
  - Center for the Humanities at Tufts Newsletter, 2018-04-23; UA243.003.00030; 1 Digital Object(s); .24 Megabytes